Andy Gross

1800 Bryant Street Apt. 305 - San Francisco, CA 94110

 \square +1 (415) 335 6775 • \square andy@andygross.org • \square about.andygross.org • \square argv0

Summary

I'm a recognized expert on distributed systems, databases, and cloud architectures with over 15 years of experience building world class products, services, and engineering teams. I am the primary author of Riak, an influential and commercially successful NoSQL database. I'm seeking technology/product leadership and founder opportunities at venture funded startups.

Experience

Opsee San Francisco, CA

Co-founder and CTO

2/2015-7/2015

A developer-oriented monitoring company founded with friends. I brought investors into our 1.5 MM seed round, hired the initial engineering team, and led implementation of the MVP product.

Twitter San Francisco, CA

Staff Software Engineer, Core Storage

3/2014-2/2015

I was a technical lead for Manhattan, Twitter's self-serve internal DBaaS, and other projects in the Core Storage group.

- o Implemented a distributed rate limiting and admission control system based on control theory to prevent cluster overload.
- o Authored an integration testing tool to automate verification of cluster inv ariants and correctness checking.
- o Wrote a dynamic configuration framework for Manhattan, allowing system configuration to be changed at runtime.

Basho Technologies San Francisco, CA

Chief Architect, VP of Engineering

12/2007-3/2014

I authored Riak, Basho's flagship product. I defined the technical and product direction as we grew the company from four to 140 employees in San Francisco, Cambridge, Herndon, London, and Tokyo.

- o Authored initial versions of all Basho Open Source and Enterprise software (Riak, RiakCS, Riak Enterprise Replication).
- o Built engineering team, participated in fundraising, closed deals with Fortune 50 companies (Apple, Comcast, AT&T, Verizon, State Farm).
- o Presented at conferences on distributed systems, lectured at Berkeley and Stanford on distributed systems in industry.

Mochi Media San Francisco, CA

Senior Systems Architect

5/2007-12/2007

I was hired as employee #3. I helped secure funding from Accel and rewrote MVP infrastructure (messaging, monitoring, DevOps tools) to handle post-launch growth. I left to start Basho with Akamai colleagues.

Apple Cupertino, CA

Distributed Systems Engineer, Developer Tools

9/2005-5/2007

I was recruited onto the Xcode team to write a distributed compiler to speed up build time for Apple's largest third party developers (Adobe, Microsoft).

- o Designed and implemented a distributed filesystem (see Patents and Publications).
- o Maintenance and feature development for the Xcode build system.
- o Presented work at WWDC 2006.

Akamai Technologies Cambridge, MA

Senior Software Engineer, Government and Custom Engineering, Systems Engineering

7/1999–9/2005

Employee #75. I was hired to carry 21" CRT monitors for new hires, and left as a Senior Engineer leading design and development of custom high-margin products for the US Government.

- o Implemented a reactive overlay network for a government customer that became the basis for Akamai's highly profitable IP acceleration products.
- o Created an analytics application aggregating IDS, BGP, and performance data for the US Intelligence Community.
- o Developed Akamai Content Storage, the distributed storage system backing the initial Apple iTunes Music Store launch.

Patents and Publications

Bumgarner, William, Adam Swift, and Andrew Gross (2012). "MIRRORED FILE SYSTEM". US8286127 B2. Gross, Andrew R. (2012). "The Architecture of Open Source Applications". In: vol. i. Chap. Riak and Erlang.

Education

University of Connecticut

Management, Finance,

Storrs, CT 1996–1999